<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-US"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed/by_tag/TypeScript.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-US" /><updated>2026-01-14T13:53:07+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed/by_tag/TypeScript.xml</id><title type="html">Vadym Nastoiashchyi</title><subtitle>Software quality fanatic | Software Engineer in Test</subtitle><author><name>Vadym Nastoiashchyi</name></author><entry><title type="html">🤔What is the best code editor for JavaScript?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/what-is-the-best-code-editor-for-javascript" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="🤔What is the best code editor for JavaScript?" /><published>2024-04-24T22:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2024-04-24T22:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/what-is-the-best-code-editor-for-javascript</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/what-is-the-best-code-editor-for-javascript"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/2024-04-24-what-is-the-best-code-editor-for-javascript/1_TwKeZwaE-NnmdBJF4iGEgQ.webp" alt="_config.yml" class="align-center border max-width-600px" /></p>

<p>JavaScript is one of the world’s most popular programming languages. JavaScript provides integration with CSS and HTML to create robust front-end applications. The introduction of NodeJS has extended the reach of high-level, interpreted programming languages to server-side development. JavaScript also plays an important role in test automation for building test frameworks for testing E2E, API, unit, etc.</p>

<h3 id="ide-vs-code-editor-comparison"><strong>IDE vs Code editor comparison</strong></h3>

<p>Code editors usually offer different types of syntax highlighting for different programming languages, but do not have additional features that are usually included in IDEs. An IDE, on the other hand, is a powerful tool that combines everything you need to create programs in one interface, including code editing, compilation, debugging, version control, and other features.</p>

<h3 id="differences-between-a-code-editor-and-an-ide">Differences between a code editor and an IDE:</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong><em>Functionality</em></strong>: A code editor is primarily a tool for editing text. An IDE, on the other hand, provides not only code editing but also tools for compiling, calling, and debugging programs, integrating with version control systems, etc.
<strong><em>Complexity</em></strong>: Due to their focus on multifunctionality, IDEs can be more difficult to learn and use, especially for beginners. Text editors, although they have less functionality, are simpler and more accessible by default.
<strong><em>Performance</em></strong>: IDEs typically require more system resources than text editors because of the additional functions and services they perform. Text editors may be more efficient on less powerful systems.
<strong><em>Scalability</em></strong>: IDEs typically provide better support for large projects with multiple files and directories through integration with version control systems and project navigation.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="code-editor"><strong>Code Editor</strong></h3>

<p>[<strong><em>Visual Studio Code](https://code.visualstudio.com/)</em></strong> (VS Code) has many advantages and disadvantages that may influence your choice of the main code editor.</p>

<p><img src="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/2024-04-24-what-is-the-best-code-editor-for-javascript/1_W3X4D4YdVl5JbWOlGqzHrg.webp" alt="_config.yml" class="align-center border max-width-600px" /></p>

<h3 id="pros-of-visual-studio-code"><strong><em>Pros of Visual Studio Code:</em></strong></h3>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong><em>Ease of use:</em></strong> VS Code has a simple and intuitive user interface that is easy to understand.
<strong><em>Extension system: **</em>hundreds of free extensions are available for VS Code, providing code hints, version control, support for various programming languages, and much more.
**<em>Integration with Git:</em> **Visual Studio Code integrates with Git right out of the box, making it easy to control versions and collaborate with teams.
**<em>Large community:</em></strong> due to its popularity, VS Code has a large audience of users, which means that you can easily find help in solving problems if they arise.
<em><strong>VS Code is completely free</strong>.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="cons-of-visual-studio-code"><strong><em>Cons of Visual Studio Code:</em></strong></h3>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong><em>It loads slower when the project is very large:</em></strong> VS Code can be slower than some other text editors at the start, especially if you have installed many extensions.
<strong><em>Moderate resource consumption:</em></strong> even though it is indeed faster than most IDEs, VS Code can still consume a significant amount of resources, especially when processing large files or using many tabs.
<strong><em>Possible problems with extensions:</em> **Although extensions and their impact on VS Code are mostly a plus, some of them can cause problems on their own, such as consuming more memory or making an entire program work improperly.
**<em>Lack of certain IDE features:</em></strong> Although VS Code works very well as a code editor, it still lacks some features that may be available in full-fledged IDEs, such as a more powerful debugger, code refactoring, etc.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="ide"><strong>IDE</strong></h3>

<p>[<em>**WebStorm](https://www.jetbrains.com/webstorm/) **</em>— is a powerful JavaScript IDE with a wide range of tools, including automatic code formatting, and deep support for various libraries and frameworks.</p>

<p><img src="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/2024-04-24-what-is-the-best-code-editor-for-javascript/1__9ZZkn3xxJM50ciW8Kalog.webp" alt="_config.yml" class="align-center border max-width-600px" /></p>

<h3 id="pros-of-webstorm"><em>Pros of WebStorm:</em></h3>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong><em>Deep JavaScript support</em></strong>: WebStorm has built-in JavaScript support, and it understands the most current JS standards, frameworks, libraries, and architectures.
<strong><em>Comprehensiveness: **</em>WebStorm supports many programming languages and technologies such as HTML, CSS, SASS, TypeScript, Node.js, etc., making it a one-stop solution for web development.
**<em>Extended set of tools:</em></strong> WebStorm includes a version control system, a more powerful debugger, refactoring tools, etc.
<strong><em>Smart code completion:</em></strong> This is one of the strongest points of the IDE, as it improves performance and usually helps to find an error before the code is run.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="cons-of-webstorm"><em>Cons of WebStorm:</em></h3>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong><em>Workload:</em></strong> WebStorm is a powerful IDE with many features, and can be a bit overwhelming in terms of interface for beginners.
<strong><em>Resource consumption: **</em>Due to its multifunctionality, WebStorm is a big consumer of system resources.
**<em>Cost:</em></strong> Unlike some other editors and IDEs such as VS Code, WebStorm is not free. It offers users one month for free and then $82 for the first-year license.
<em>**Slow updates: **</em>Although JetBrains supports its products well, sometimes the release of updates can be slow.
<em>**Need for customization: **</em>Unlike some other code editors that “work right out of the box”, WebStorm may require significant customization before you can get started.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>[<strong>JetBrains Fleet](https://www.jetbrains.com/fleet/)</strong> — is a new product from JetBrains, and although it is still in the developer access phase, some advantages and disadvantages can already be identified. I believe it is a symbiosis of VS Code design and WebStorm power.</p>

<p><img src="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/2024-04-24-what-is-the-best-code-editor-for-javascript/1_LZXprgJRNWgek2wbm5gtNw.webp" alt="_config.yml" class="align-center border max-width-600px" /></p>

<h3 id="pros-of-jetbrains-fleet"><em>Pros of JetBrains Fleet:</em></h3>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong><em>Lightness and speed: **</em>One of the main goals of JetBrains Fleet is to make writing and editing code as easy and fast as possible. It uses the latest technologies to optimize the performance of tasks that have high resource requirements. Fleet is “lighter” than WebStorm, but VS Code is still faster and easier.
**<em>A new approach to navigation:</em></strong> JetBrains Fleet introduces the concept of “Non-modal UI”, which allows you to easily switch between different viewing modes, including code view, function calls, project structure, etc.
<em>**Built-in Git support: **</em>Like most JetBrains products, Fleet has built-in Git support for easy code version control.
<em>**Extensibility: **</em>JetBrains Fleet provides an API for creating extensions, allowing developers to customize it to their needs.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="cons-of-jetbrains-fleet">Cons of JetBrains Fleet:</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong><em>New product:</em></strong> Since Fleet is a relatively new product, it may have some nuances or bugs that have not yet been fully resolved by the developers.
<strong><em>Limited extensions: **</em>Currently, the availability of extensions is limited as Fleet is still in its early stages of development.
**<em>Reduced language support: **</em>Currently, support for some programming languages may be limited or incomplete.
**<em>Price:</em></strong> Currently free. In the future, it will be a paid solution.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Please note that JetBrains Fleet is still under active development, and these pros and cons may change.</p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion:</h3>

<p>The choice between an IDE and a text editor depends on your personal development needs. It’s important to remember that the best choice is the one that best suits your specific needs or your workflow.</p>

<p><strong><em>Thanks to everyone who read this article to the end, I hope you found it useful.</em></strong></p>]]></content><author><name>Vadym Nastoiashchyi</name></author><category term="JavaScript" /><category term="TypeScript" /><category term="Webstorm" /><category term="VSCode" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[JavaScript is one of the world’s most popular programming languages. JavaScript provides integration with CSS and HTML to create robust front-end applications. The introduction of NodeJS has extended the reach of high-level, interpreted programming languages to server-side development. JavaScript also plays an important role in test automation for building test frameworks for testing E2E, API, unit, etc...]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/2024-04-24-what-is-the-best-code-editor-for-javascript/1_TwKeZwaE-NnmdBJF4iGEgQ.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/2024-04-24-what-is-the-best-code-editor-for-javascript/1_TwKeZwaE-NnmdBJF4iGEgQ.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">JavaScript 🆚 TypeScript in Test Automation. A Closer Look at Playwright and Cypress</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/javascript-typescript-in-test-automation-a-closer-look-at-playwright-and-cypress" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JavaScript 🆚 TypeScript in Test Automation. A Closer Look at Playwright and Cypress" /><published>2024-04-01T22:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2024-04-01T22:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/javascript-typescript-in-test-automation-a-closer-look-at-playwright-and-cypress</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/javascript-typescript-in-test-automation-a-closer-look-at-playwright-and-cypress"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/2024-04-01-javascript-typescript-in-test-automation-a-closer-look-at-playwright-and-cypress/0_awmiCTtuNj9yrQQ4.webp" alt="_config.yml" class="align-center border max-width-600px" /></p>

<p>For any software development project, selecting the right language and tools is crucial to ensure effective test automation. Two languages that have caught the attention of developers worldwide are JavaScript (JS) and TypeScript (TS). Let’s dive into a comparison between these two languages, and specifically how they apply in two popular testing tools — Playwright and Cypress.</p>

<h3 id="javascript-vs-typescript"><strong><em>JavaScript VS TypeScript:</em></strong></h3>

<p>JavaScript, a high-level interpreted language, has proven its worth due to its compatibility across browsers. This dynamic language has an easy learning curve and is the backbone of many frameworks and libraries used in web development.</p>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong><em>Pros:</em></strong></p>
  <ul>
    <li><em>Ease of Use:</em> JavaScript has a less steep learning curve and is easier to set up. It’s ideal for beginners who want to start coding quickly.</li>
    <li><em>Flexibility:</em> JavaScript is dynamically typed, allowing more flexibility in writing code.</li>
    <li><em>Popularity:</em> Being around for a long time, JavaScript has a large community, abundant resources, and widespread support across browsers and platforms.
<strong>Cons:</strong></li>
    <li>*Lack of Type Safety: *The biggest drawback of JavaScript is its lack of static type-checking, increasing the possibility of runtime errors.</li>
    <li><em>Less Suitable for large-scale applications:</em> For complex applications, the lack of static types can lead to difficulties in maintaining and scaling the codebase.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<p>On the other hand, TypeScript, a statically typed superset of JavaScript, offers additional features like type checking that catches potential bugs at compile time. TypeScript enhances code quality and understandability, hence making maintenance easier.</p>

<p>However, TypeScript’s learning curve is steeper compared to JavaScript. It may also require additional setup time, as TypeScript code has to be transpiled to JavaScript to run in a browser.</p>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Pros:</strong></p>
  <ul>
    <li><em>Static Type-Checking:</em> TypeScript’s main advantage is its ability to check types at compile time, allowing for early error detection.</li>
    <li>*Scalability: *TypeScript is more structured and robust, making it best suited for large-scale project development.</li>
    <li><em>Down Compilation:</em> TypeScript code can be compiled down to a JavaScript version for broader browser compatibility.
<strong>Cons:</strong></li>
    <li><em>Learning Curve:</em> TypeScript has a steeper learning curve than JavaScript due to its typing system and more complex syntax.</li>
    <li><em>Compilation Step:</em> TypeScript needs an extra compilation step to transpile down to JavaScript, which can slow down development.</li>
    <li><em>Verbose Syntax:</em> Due to static typing and advanced features, TypeScript can have more verbose syntax compared to JavaScript.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<p>In a nutshell, the choice between JavaScript and TypeScript comes down to your team’s skills and the requirements of your project. Your decision may also depend on your development environment: If your team values type safety and uses large codebases, TypeScript could be the better choice. If your team consists of novice programmers coding a small project, JavaScript may be the way to go.</p>

<h3 id="playwright-and-cypress-javascript-vs-typescript"><strong><em>Playwright and Cypress JavaScript vs TypeScript:</em></strong></h3>

<p><a href="https://playwright.dev/">Playwright</a> and <a href="https://www.cypress.io/">Cypress</a> are two advanced, modern automation testing tools that can be used with both JavaScript and TypeScript. Playwright supports multiple browsers and offers fast, reliable, and capable automation for web components by using the modern browser API. Alternatively, Cypress focuses on providing a comprehensive end-to-end testing experience.</p>

<p>Choosing between JavaScript and TypeScript when working with Playwright and Cypress depends on various factors, including your team’s skillset, the complexity of the project, and personal preference.</p>

<p><strong><em>JavaScript:</em></strong></p>

<p><strong>Playwright</strong> — Choosing JavaScript could make sense if your team is more comfortable with dynamic typing or if you want to avoid the setup that TypeScript requires. Also, if your project isn’t very complex and doesn’t require the added type of safety that TypeScript provides, then using JavaScript could be a better choice<em>.</em></p>

<p><img src="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/2024-04-01-javascript-typescript-in-test-automation-a-closer-look-at-playwright-and-cypress/1_5ogof1Qa-HzaFLE5L1bZPA.webp" alt="_config.yml" class="align-center border max-width-600px" /></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Playwright supports JavaScript out of the box. There is nothing to configure. Only Node.js to be installed</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Cypress</strong> — was initially built to support JavaScript. If your team is more comfortable with JavaScript or if you’re working on a small to mid-sized project, using Cypress with JavaScript can be a good option.</p>

<p><img src="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/2024-04-01-javascript-typescript-in-test-automation-a-closer-look-at-playwright-and-cypress/1_D6It49zCZXwBbm1VbH6V6A.webp" alt="_config.yml" class="align-center border max-width-600px" /></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Cypress supports JavaScript out of the box. There is nothing to configure. Only Node.js to be installed</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/2024-04-01-javascript-typescript-in-test-automation-a-closer-look-at-playwright-and-cypress/0_s9gFJiK-JOtumHuQ.webp" alt="_config.yml" class="align-center border max-width-600px" /><em>Cypress with JS</em></p>

<p><strong><em>TypeScript</em></strong>:</p>

<p><strong>Playwright</strong> — TypeScript could be a better choice for larger, more complex projects where type safety can help prevent bugs. By catching errors early at compile time, you can save time and resources that would have been spent finding and fixing them at runtime. TypeScript also provides better autocompletion, making it easier to use Playwright APIs.</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>To support TypeScript, you must specify Playwright during the initial installation:</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/2024-04-01-javascript-typescript-in-test-automation-a-closer-look-at-playwright-and-cypress/0_s9gFJiK-JOtumHuQ.webp" alt="_config.yml" class="align-center border max-width-600px" /><em>Just choose your preferred programming language — and the Playwright does it all.</em></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Or install everything listed manually:</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
  <li><strong>add <a href="http://www.typescriptlang.org/docs/handbook/tsconfig-json.html">tsconfig.json</a></strong></li>
</ul>

<p><img src="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/2024-04-01-javascript-typescript-in-test-automation-a-closer-look-at-playwright-and-cypress/1_VuFoqxkXr1AcuJY9TAuqgA.webp" alt="_config.yml" class="align-center border max-width-600px" /><em>To use all TypeScript “magic” use command <strong>“npx tsc -p tsconfig.json — noEmit -w”</strong></em></p>

<p>[<strong><em>Playwright TypeScript configuration example](https://github.com/VadimNastoyashchy/playwright-saucedemo.com)</em></strong></p>

<p><strong>Cypress</strong> — However, if type safety is crucial for your project, or if you’re working on a larger codebase, TypeScript could be the better choice. TypeScript’s static typing can help catch errors during compile-time before they crash your application. This feature, combined with improved autocompletion and tooling support, often leads to cleaner, more maintainable codebases.</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>To support TypeScript, you must install the nessesary dependancy and add ts configuration:</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong><em>npm install — save-dev typescript</em></strong></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>add <a href="http://www.typescriptlang.org/docs/handbook/tsconfig-json.html">tsconfig.json</a></strong></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://github.com/VadimNastoyashchy/demoblaze.com">Cypress TypeScript configuration example</a></p>

<p>In conclusion, choosing between JavaScript and TypeScript, and between Playwright and Cypress, depends on your project needs, team skills, and specific requirements. TypeScript, combined with Playwright or Cypress, is an excellent choice for large-scale projects where reliability, maintainability, and advanced features are crucial. On the other hand, JavaScript, because of its simplicity, remains a solid choice for quick and effective test automation.</p>

<p><strong><em>Thanks to everyone who read this article to the end, I hope you found it useful.</em></strong></p>

<p>Sources used in the article:
<a href="https://github.com/VadimNastoyashchy/playwright-saucedemo.com">https://github.com/VadimNastoyashchy/playwright-saucedemo.com</a>
<a href="https://github.com/VadimNastoyashchy/demoblaze.com">https://github.com/VadimNastoyashchy/demoblaze.com</a>
<a href="https://docs.cypress.io/guides/tooling/typescript-support">https://docs.cypress.io/guides/tooling/typescript-support</a>
<a href="https://playwright.dev/docs/test-typescript">https://playwright.dev/docs/test-typescript</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Vadym Nastoiashchyi</name></author><category term="JavaScript" /><category term="TypeScript" /><category term="Cypress" /><category term="Playwright" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For any software development project, selecting the right language and tools is crucial to ensure effective test automation. Two languages that have caught the attention of developers worldwide are JavaScript (JS) and TypeScript (TS). Let’s dive into a comparison between these two languages, and specifically how they apply in two popular testing tools — Playwright and Cypress...]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/2024-04-01-javascript-typescript-in-test-automation-a-closer-look-at-playwright-and-cypress/0_awmiCTtuNj9yrQQ4.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/2024-04-01-javascript-typescript-in-test-automation-a-closer-look-at-playwright-and-cypress/0_awmiCTtuNj9yrQQ4.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>